<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of The cry of the innocent for justice being a brief narrative of the illegal apphrehending and imprisoning of about seven score of the people called Quakers, by souldiers without justice or due prosecution of the law, who now suffer in Newgate for the testimony of a pure conscience, and because they cannot sin against God. And also a short relation of the proceedings of the court at the sessions at Old Baley, towards the said prisoners, held the first day, and the fifth day of this instant month called July. As also divers particular proceedings of Alderman Brown towards that people truly related and worthy of sober mens observation; with quotations of divers antient laws of England proving the unjustness, and how contrary to the law of the land, the said apprehending and imprisoning of the said people is. Collected and put to publick view by the aforesaid prisoners.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58998</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830589</idno>
  <idno type="VID">35042</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264215012</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219053</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830589</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99830589e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58998)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1875:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of The cry of the innocent for justice being a brief narrative of the illegal apphrehending and imprisoning of about seven score of the people called Quakers, by souldiers without justice or due prosecution of the law, who now suffer in Newgate for the testimony of a pure conscience, and because they cannot sin against God. And also a short relation of the proceedings of the court at the sessions at Old Baley, towards the said prisoners, held the first day, and the fifth day of this instant month called July. As also divers particular proceedings of Alderman Brown towards that people truly related and worthy of sober mens observation; with quotations of divers antient laws of England proving the unjustness, and how contrary to the law of the land, the said apprehending and imprisoning of the said people is. Collected and put to publick view by the aforesaid prisoners.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24, 33-48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page torn and stained; quire D lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Prisoners' writings, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35042:1"/>
            <p>THE Second Part OF THE Cry of the Innocent for Iustice, Being a Brief Narrative of the Illegal Apprehending and Imprisoning of about seven score of the people Called <hi>QƲAKERS,</hi> By Souldiers without Justice or due prosecution of Law, who now suffer in <hi>Newgate</hi> for the Testimony of a pure Conscience, and because they cannot sin against God.</p>
            <p>And also a short Relation of the proceedings of the Court at the Sessions at <hi>Old Baley,</hi> towards the said Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, held the first day, and the fifth day of this instant month called <hi>July.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As also divers particular proceedings of Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> towards that people truly related and worthy of sober mens Observation; with Quotations of divers Ancient Laws of <hi>England,</hi> proving the unjustness, and how contrary to the Law of the Land, the said apprehending and imprisoning of the said people is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected and put to publick view by the aforesaid Prisoners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for the Author, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35042:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35042:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Lord God everlasting hath gathered us to be a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and hath Created us for his praise, and formed us for himself, that we should be, and do, and suffer according to his good pleasure, and our Souls can say even when the Cup of Afflictions appears the deepest for us to drink, not our will, but thy will O Father be done, and this is the frame of our Spirit.</p>
            <p>And seeing we are thus called of God to give our witness this day by these bonds of suffering, we are resolved into patience and long suffering and faithfulnesse, even till the Lord deliver us, for we have in good earnest committed our Cause to him, it is spread before him, and known to him, let him do what he will; We are assured our Sighs, and Groans, and Prayers are entred into his Heart, and our Tears are put in his Bottle, and every hour of our afflictions are accounted by him, and our Cause is entred into the secret of his Heart to meditate; And again we say, let him arise when he pleases, let him bring deliverance how he will; for we are not weary of our Afflictions though they are great, because they are for the Lord, for his Name, his Truth and Worship sake, and the Love and Zeal that we have for him, makes all things easie which we do or suffer for him, and our afflictions are not worthy to be compared with that weight of Glory, with that fulnesse of Joy, Peace and Comfort which we possess in our Souls, in so much that we can say verily the Lord is good though men be evil, he is Merciful, Compassionate, and full of loving Kindnesse, Gentleness, and all good Virtues, though men be hard-hearted, cruel, and full of despite against his People, and our God is not wanting to us in that very moment when men shuts up their hearts in hardness and will not hear our cry, and it is onely the kindness of the Lord by which our Souls and Bodies live
<pb facs="tcp:35042:3"/> this day, and therefore he is worthy, he is worthy, and we ascribe unto him Honour and Glory, Authority and Power, now and for ever more.</p>
            <p>Reader, Necessity requires the publishing of these things for the information and satisfacton of the world, and to prevent the many false retorts that otherwise may go abroad concerning these things, and such is our love to truth in all Cases, that we would have all to know the truth of all things related to us, and we hope none can justly be offended hereat, for seeing that such and such things are said of us in the world, as if we were a people not fit to live, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is expedient that we publish the proceedings of others towards us, and our proceedings towards others, which we desire to do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniously, and as truly as God hath given us understandings to do, and when, what we have said and done towards others, and what others have said and done towards us, are brought to l ght and truly considered; The judgement therefore we must leave to the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of God in all people, for this is our day of Tryal, and we desire that all may know how it is with us, who are such as fear the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and fears not what man can do unto us.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Newgate</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>22d. of the 5th. Month, 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>The Epistle Dedicatory to Alderman <hi>Richard Brown.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RICHARD BROWN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou art not sealed up already for destruction, and if repentance be not utterly hid from thy eyes, The Lord convert thee, and forgive thee of all thy hard and cruel dealing towards us, we desire thy repentance rather then thy destruction, and the Lord God of Heaven and Earth give judgement of final determination between thee and us, that all the earth may know whether thy cause against us, or our cause be just before him who onely is the Righteous Judge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35042:3"/>
            <head>A brief Account of the cruel and barbarous manner of the taking and imprisoning of the People of God (called Quakers) beginning at the eleventh day of the moneth called <hi>May, 1662.</hi> untill the fifth of the 5th. moneth called <hi>July,</hi> under pretence of executing the late Act of Parliament.</head>
            <p>IT hath alwayes been the portion of those who will live godly in Christ Jesus to suffer persecution, (and as it hath been so it is) he that is born and lives after the flesh, persecutes him that is born, and lives in and after the spirit, and such are those of whom this is a Relation. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the eleventh day of the Month called <hi>May,</hi> 1662. divers persons (called <hi>Quakers</hi>) were met together in the peace and fear of God, according to the Example of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians, in a house in <hi>Johns-street Middlesex,</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Sepulchers London,</hi> there came into their Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly one <hi>Philip Miller</hi> in a rude and boistrous manner, who laid hold with violence upon several persons called Quakers, and commanded the Rabble who attended him for that ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to secure whom he pleased, the which they were ready to do, although the said <hi>Miller</hi> was no Officer, neither had any Order or Warrant for his so doing, onely to colour his wickedness he setched a Constable, who was not willing to come because he had no Warrant, yet was forced to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him because of his threats; and the said <hi>Miller</hi> commanded the Constable to go along with him, and the five Prisoners, with those of his company that he thought good to guard them, and carried them before Justice <hi>Powel</hi> (so called) who committed them without any reproof to the said <hi>Miller</hi> for his wicked, illegal and cruel dealing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the innocent, though he was informed of his mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, but sent the persons aforesaid to New pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
            <p>And upon the third day following, being the 13. of the month aforesaid, the said <hi>Miller</hi> did again in his former
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35042:4"/> manner, come into the same place, where were met together a small company of the people aforesaid in the peace and fear of God; and after a little space began to pull and beat some there present, having a long cane in his hand, because they would not depart at his command, and took whom he pleased and charged the Constables whom he brought along with him to secure them and take them into custody; the Constables themselves being moderate and unwilling to meddle, having no Warrant or Authority requiring them so to do, neither doth the late Act of Parliament require it of them, the name of a Constable not being mentioned throughout the whole Act, neither particularly nor in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensive terms, as was manifest to them in reading of the Act before them; Yet notwithstanding the said <hi>Miller</hi> threatned the Constables, and pulled and haled whom he pleased, and commanded the Constables as if he had been an Officer and they such as were to be commanded by him, and for want of an order was this disorder committed, and the innocent abused; and the Justice before whom they were carried as aforesaid would take no notice of the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and violence offered to them; but the next day being a Sessions at <hi>Hicks-hall</hi> for <hi>Middlesex,</hi> he sent them thither without Mittemus or Warrnt, taking their words for the night before to come to his house that morning, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly they performed, and sent away to <hi>Hicks-hall</hi> as aforesaid, where after some examination by the Justices, nine of them were committed to new Prison, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Act of Parliament under pretence of which they were committed doth not give power to Justices of Peace in Counties to commit before conviction, as was urged to them by the Prisoners at the bar, they being restrained by the said Act, onely to proceed as in case of trespass, (but otherwise they may proceed in Corporations) yet were the Prisoners committed to New Prison where they remained for some dayes, and then were sent to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where they are now continued, but were first indited at the Sessions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid.</p>
            <p>And upon the 25. of the month aforesaid, there were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> 39. persons called Quakers,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35042:4"/> by Captain <hi>Reeves</hi> (so called) and some Souldiers who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied him for that service, they violently rushed into the meeting with Musquets, Swords drawn and other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, who with violence pulled down him that was declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fear and power of God; as also another who desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to shew his order for his so doing, to which the said <hi>Reeves</hi> replyed he would not in that place, for indeed he could not as afterward appeared, yet he with his Souldiers violently haled several persons out of the meeting and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them away, and as he went, forced others to go along with him out of the Streets, though they were not at the meeting, and carried them all into <hi>Pauls Yard,</hi> and caused a guard to be set about them where they continued till their Publick worship was ended there, and when it was done then Sir <hi>Richard Brown</hi> (so called) came unto the place where the Prisoners were guarded, then the said <hi>Reeve</hi> separated four of the Prisoners from the rest and caused them to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed to the said Major General, who as soon as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held them, was so transported with passion, that in great rage and fury laid hands first on a very aged person, and with violence pulled him down by the hat brims, so he ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him twice, and the last time the said aged man quite lost his hat which he valued at thirty shillings; he also ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved another in like manner, and a Souldier (whether by his command or not he knows) struck this last person on the bare head with a pistol a great blow) and in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (the said Major General) used the other two, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver called or examined the rest, neither were any of the four last mentioned examined, concerning any crime or offence by them done or committed, but forthwith sent them all to <hi>Newgate</hi> by Souldiers, which was done accordingly, and received by the Goaler without Mittimus or Order in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, where they were kept for some dayes, that their rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and acquaintance many times were not suffered to come at them, though the conditions of the Prisoners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it, they being generally Tradesmen and Masters of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and others poor who lived by their daily labour, who now do not onely suffer themselves but their whole families with them, and all this not onely against Law, but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35042:5"/> because for conscience sake they cannot forsake the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the People of God, to worship him according as they are perswaded in their hearts and consciences, who have no other end in their Meeting together, but to edifie one another in the knowledge of Gods wayes and mind, and of the truth hereof the God of Heaven is witness, yet for no other cause they remain prisoners in <hi>Newgate</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said.</p>
            <p>And upon the day aforesaid were taken from the snaile in Towerstreet by Souldiers without any Warrant twenty one persons called Quakers, for no other things then the causes aforesaid, and were carried by the said armed men to the Exchange, and there kept for some time, and then carried before <hi>Richard Brown</hi> as aforesaid, who laid violent hands on some of them, and did kick and strike others, and ordered one to be put among the Fellons, because he reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>R. Brown</hi> (when he the said Major General smote the prisoner with his fist on the face, and kicked him on the shin) and said, what <hi>Richard,</hi> wilt thou turn murderer? thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est not do so when I was a Souldier under thy Command at <hi>Abingdon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This Person was in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Pratis Company there.</note> and thou commanded me with others to search peoples houses for Pyes and Roast-meat, because they kept Christ-mass (as a holy time) and brought the persons pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners to the guard, for observing the same; Then one standing by that was supposed to be of his Family, said there is an <hi>Abingdon</hi> bird, then <hi>Richard Brown</hi> said he is a Rogue for all that, and struck him with his fist under the chin, whereupon another prisoner said what; a Magistrate and strike! upon which the Major General laid both his hands upon his hat brims to pull him to the ground, and then commanded the Souldiers to take them all away and carry them to <hi>Newgate,</hi> the which they did without Mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus or Order in writing, where they remain strictly kept; their Relations and Friends for some dayes denyed to come unto them, though they be Tradesmen and such as live by their dayly labours as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And upon the same day were taken six persons called Quakers out of their Meeting near <hi>Wheeler</hi> Street by Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the manner aforesaid, and for no other cause then
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35042:5"/> meeting together as aforesaid, and were carried before the Lieutenant of the Tower, who committed them to <hi>Newgate</hi> where they remain prisoners.</p>
            <p>Upon the first day of the fourth month called <hi>June,</hi> being the first day of the week, the people of God, in scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> were met together in the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth,</hi> according to their usual manner, that place being their own hired house, where they have kept their peaceable Meetings for the Worship of God these many years. And being that day met in the fear of God with their hearts lifted up towards him, and a Servant of God amongst them being declaring the Word of the Lord, in order to the Salvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that sinners might be converted unto God, and the Saints strengthened in the Faith which gives victory over all the World, the pretious Power and Presence of the Lord God being amongst them in their meeting, to the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Assembly of the Saints, in the very interim rushed into the house, and amongst them a company of rude Soulders, very violently running upon the people, coming in with Swords drawn, lighted Matches, and in a war-like posture, and marched with much threats up the Meeting, chuling and kicking the people as they passed, till they came to him that was declaring in the fear of God as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, violently falling upon him with Swords, and Musquets, and Pikes advanced towards him, (who yet seemed as little to fear them, as they seemed to fear God, which was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all) and rudely and violently they pulled him down from the place where he stood, ratling Swords and Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets over his head (though no harm he obtained, but that was more Gods providence then their favour) and they passionately haled him away out of the Meeting without moderation, pitty or man-like compassion, rejoycing as if they had obtained a Noble Victory, in that (cowards-like) a company of rudely armed fellows had made a vapour with drawn Swords and cocked Musquets, among a Meeting of the poor people of God, who had hardly (it may be) as much as a knife amongst them, and whom they knew would not lift up a hand against them, and had domineered much like the Simile, When a company of Dogs goes among a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35042:6"/> flock of sheep. Well but they conducted their Prisoner (thus unhumanely taken) by force of Arms along, till they brought him to their Captain at the main Guard at <hi>Pauls,</hi> who took him into custody, and without any examination committed him Prisoner to the Guard; And then the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers returned again to the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth,</hi> where their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, and Threats, and Carriages, were much like as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is mentioned; and the Meeting being still kept toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they apprehended two more of the Friends, and in like manner haled them out, and carried them to <hi>Pauls,</hi> and committed them also to the main Guard for some hours, till the Captain came to them and told them he was to send them to <hi>Newgate</hi> immediately, to whom the Prisoners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, they conceived he had no Legal Power to send them to Prison; they expected first to be brought before some Civil Magistrate of the City; and before him charged with some breach of Law, and duly and orderly proceeded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all according to the Law of the Land ere they were sent to Newgate, telling the Captain what had Military men to do with them, and why should Souldiers meddle with them contrary to the good Laws of the Land, they told him they were civil men and not found in Arms, and if they had broke any Law, the cognisance thereof pertained to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yor or some Magistrate of the Law of the City; As for Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, what had they to do with us, and why should they usurp Authority by Military power over Free-men? And to this purpose they Objected against the proceedings; but such was the disposition of the Captain, that <hi>English</hi> Law and Freedom might as well have been pleaded to a <hi>Turk</hi> in <hi>Turkey,</hi> as to him in that place, for he seemed resolved to obey his Major General, by whose commission he acted, and notwithstanding what of Reason or Law could be said, he caused a party of his men to conduct his said three Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where the Goaler received them without asking who they were, whence they came, or for what they were sent; and being detained there for some hours, the Souldiers came for them again, and took them out, and guarded them to Sir <hi>Richard Brown;</hi> (so called) where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before him, he asked their names and places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35042:6"/> told one <hi>John Parrot, What, you have been at</hi> Rome <hi>to subvert,</hi> but recalling himself said, <hi>to convert the Pope, John</hi> told him, He had suffered at <hi>Rome</hi> for the Testimony of Jesus, to to which <hi>R. Brown</hi> replyed, <hi>If ye had converted the Pope to your Religion, I should have liked him far worse then I do now,</hi> but <hi>John</hi> replyed, God would have liked him better; But after some more short discourse, being told by them, he did not proceed duly according to the late Act of Parliament against us; He committed them to <hi>Newgate,</hi> to which place they were guarded again by the Souldiers, and was there kept for some dayes after so close, that their friends and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance were for some time denyed to come to them, which practise was abhorred by the Heathen, as may be seen by their carriage unto <hi>Paul</hi> recorded in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> where the Magistrates commanded their frinds and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance should not be forbidden to come to them.</p>
            <p>And upon the day aforesaid, were violently and by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men taken from <hi>Mile-end</hi> out of a Meeting by Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, several persons (called <hi>Quakers</hi>) that were assembled in the Peace and Fear of God, and carried before the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the Tower, and by him sent to New Prison, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thirteen in number, of which some were taken by the way, and one was taken in the Tower, onely for coming to see what became of his friends, in which Prison they remain, their relations and friends for some time denyed to come unto them.</p>
            <p>And upon the eight day of the fourth month called <hi>June,</hi> were taken from the Meeting near <hi>Wheeler</hi> street (Assembled in the Peace and Fear of God) fourteen of the people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers,</hi> by Souldiers, and carried before <hi>John Robinson</hi> Lieutenant of the Tower, who committed them to New Prison where they remain, their usage is in manner as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, some of them are now in the common Goal.</p>
            <p>And upon the same day aforesaid, were taken by Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from <hi>Mile-end</hi> eight persons called <hi>Quakers,</hi> out of a peaceable Meeting there, and carried before the said <hi>John Robinson</hi> Lieutenant of the Tower, who forthwith commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to New Prison, where they remain strict and close
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35042:7"/> kept, and their relations not suffered to come unto them, but sometimes as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And upon the fifteenth of the month called <hi>June,</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> being met at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> the usual place of their assembling, in the Peace and Fear of God, There came into their Meeting one <hi>Cox,</hi> said to be a Wine-cooper in <hi>Seethin</hi>-lane with certain Souldiers follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with Swords drawn, in a Rude, Cruel and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous manner, beating both men and women, regarding neither Age or Sex, and breaking also the houshold-stuff to pieces that was there; whereupon one present asked him if he had any Order or Warrant for what he did, they being alwayes willing to obey all legal proceedings, but instead of shewing any Order, the said <hi>Cox</hi> struck the party on the face, and commanded the Souldiers to take him to the Guard; and when they had done beating and exercising their cruelty upon the innocent, they forced them out of the Meeting, without doers, being two men called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who were sorely bruised and beaten, they not being willing to go without a Warrant or Order shewed unto them, the Souldiers carried them both upon Musquets into <hi>Pauls</hi> yard, and when they laid them down, they dragged one of them by the heels on his back and head in a very inhumane man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; This being done, the said Wine-cooper was heard to say, <hi>He would go get a cup of Sack, for these Devils had even wearied him out;</hi> And no marvel he was weary, for he laid on with what strength he had until his breath was nigh gone. Yet for all this the innocent people being supported by the power of God, presently entred the Meeting again, and there continued in Gods Peace and Fear together for about one hours space, and then departed in the pure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshings of Gods Life one in another. The two friends were as aforesaid committed to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And upon the same day in the afternoon at the place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid were taken by Souldiers three Friends out of a peaceable Meeting there, and thrust by force into <hi>Newgate,</hi> the Goaler receiving of them without Mittimus or Order (onely from the Souldiers) and being asked why he would keep them Prisoners, having no Order for it, he replyed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35042:7"/> he would keep them untill he had an Order, or words to that purpose, and accordingly did so to the Sessions, and yet remains.</p>
            <p>And upon the same day was taken out of a house in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dersgate</hi> Street, where some people called Quakers were assembled in the peace and fear of God, as at other times, six persons by Souldiers without a Warrant, or Order, and being asked for an order, one lift up his Musquet, saying, this is my order, and carried them forthwith by force and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to <hi>Newgate</hi> where they remain, never being carried before any Magistrate at all to be examined, and so received and detained by the keeper as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And in the Morning at the same house about the tenth hour came the said <hi>Cox</hi> Wine Cooper, by some called an Officer, with several Souldiers, who drew his Sword and entred the house with violence, notwithstanding there was no meeting there that morning, he in a rude and barbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner threw the houshold-stuff up and down, to the endangering the woman of the house, who escaped narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from being spoyled by a forme that was thrown; then he went up into the Chamber and searched at his pleasure, pretending for arms, the man of the house asked him for his Order, and answer was returned, this is my Order, holding out his sword, so with many threatning, base unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil words uttered unto the people of the house, he and his Souldiers departed.</p>
            <p>And upon the same day were taken out of a house in <hi>Mile-end,</hi> where the people of God called Quakers were Assembled in the Peace and Fear of God as at other times, by Souldiers in a rude and wicked manner, haled five per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to their Court of Guard, who kept them there some time, and afterward carried them before <hi>John Robinson</hi> Lievetenant of the Tower, who asked them whether they would take the Oath of Allegiance, who answered, (nay,) whereupon he sent them to <hi>Newgate</hi> where they remain, though the Act of Parliament saith it should be duely and lawfully tendred, which is not done without two Justices of the Peace being present, whereof one is to be of the quorum; But how can Law be observed when Justice is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35042:8"/> or Gods Law be kept by them who regard not their own Law.</p>
            <p>And upon the same day at the time and place aforesaid, were taken by the same Souldiers, two little boyes, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the age of thirteen years, and the other about the age of sixteen or seventeen, who were brought before the said Lievetenant of the Tower, where one present told him he supposed they were not of the age of sixteen years, which according to the Act they ought to be, otherwise they are not punishable by the said Act, to which the Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant answered, they were old enough to be whipt, and they should be whipt out of their Religion, and so sent them to new <hi>Bridewell,</hi> where the next day they were put with their armes into the Stocks, and there pinched with great cruelty for two hours that their wrists were much swelled, and all this was executed upon them because they would not answer their wills in working, which they could not do to fulfil their lust, they eating nothing at their charge, but being supported by the power of God, they were not daunted by all they could do unto them, and they are still in the said Prison, rejoycing they are found worthy to suffer, and have written to all Friends Children to be faithful in bearing their Testimony for the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all wickedness and unrighteousness, whereby is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled that saying of the Holy Scripture, <hi>Out of the mouthes of Babes and Sucklings he will perfect his Praise.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also upon the 22. day of the 5. Month, the People of God being met together to Worship him at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> the usual place of their Meeting, and being peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fitting together, there came in a party of Captain <hi>Bradshawes</hi> Souldiers in a rude violent manner, according to their custome, and violently pluckt him down that was speaking, and pulled him and haled him to Prison, knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and abusing People in a rude inhumane manner, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hands violently on a Person being at prayer, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving carried the aforesaid Person to Prison; they came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and took another Friend to Prison in the like manner, and kept them till the evening, and then one of them was brought before Alderman <hi>Brown,</hi> who committed him to Prison to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where he remains till this day.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35042:8"/>
               <head>The Case of <hi>Samuel Fisher</hi> and four more Friends called Quake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> sent to <hi>Bridwell</hi> by <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> and now Prisoners in <hi>Newgate,</hi> namely, <hi>Samuel Goodaker, Henry Green, John Grimshur, John Howel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ON the 21th. day of <hi>May,</hi> 1662. There came <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Knoles</hi> and <hi>John Herbert</hi> of the Parish of <hi>Andrews<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>burn,</hi> and other Musqueters with their naked swords<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> some private dwellings, whereof 2. or 3. doores were broke<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by them, and finding four of us (and one more who is since discharged, because he was sick in <hi>Bridewell</hi> nigh unto death, <hi>viz. William Ames</hi> of <hi>Amsterdam</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi>) in 2. or 3. sever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al houses without shewing any Warrant when demanded, but their Swords, which they threatningly held up at us, saying, do not ask us for Warrant, this is our Warrant; took us away by force and arms, and marched us first to <hi>Pauls Yard</hi> where we were a laughing-stock to the Souldiers somewhile, and from thence thorow <hi>Cheapside</hi> to the old <hi>Exchange,</hi> where we were a laughing-stock to rude Souldiers another while, and from thence back again up <hi>Cheapside</hi> and thorow <hi>Newgate-Market</hi> to <hi>Richard Browns</hi> house in <hi>Ivy Lane,</hi> from whence we were sent to <hi>Bridewell</hi> with a Mittimus to be kept at hard labour at first, though the next morning that Mittimus was changed for another, wherein we were charged for unlawful Assembling our selves to Worship, and required to be kept unless we gave sureties to appear, to the next Sessions.</p>
               <p>After six weeks abode thereto the great endammaging, and almost utter undoing of some of us, being Country men whose business cannot go on in our absence, We were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented at the Bar at the Sessions House in old <hi>Baylif</hi> on Tues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <hi>July</hi> 1. Where instead of having our expected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded tryal as concerning what was charged against us, that we might either be sentenced according to the Law, if found guilty, or otherwise dismissed or discharged; we were contrary to all Law in that capacity of Prisoners
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35042:9"/> wherein we stood) required to take the Oath of Allegience, as the only business (as the Deputy Recorder said) which we were brought thither for: And when it was demanded that the Law might be read by virtue of which they requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red us then and there to take the said Oath (which as yet we had no way refused) it was promised us by the Deputy and the Court, that the Law should be read to us, instead of which they ordered the Clerk to read only the form of the Oath it self, but would not permit the Law for the imposing of it to be read at all; but before we had either declared our willingness to take it, or our refusall of it, we were commanded to be taken away, whereupon the Officers pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us away with violence, to the throwing some of us down upon the stones before the face of the Court, out of which as he passed <hi>Samuel Fisher</hi> spake to this purpose, <hi>viz.</hi> Take notice People, that we have not yet refused to take the Oath, but the Court refuseth to perform their promise, that the Statute for it should be read, which they made but just now before you all; If such doings as this ever prosper, it must be when there is no God.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>John Howel,</hi> he was sent to <hi>Bridewell</hi> to work by <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> because he did not tell him on the sudden what was his name, and being demanded at the Court why he did not tell his name, he replyed he was beaten and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the presence of <hi>Richard Brown</hi> when he was brought before him; <hi>Richard Brown</hi> asking him wherein were you abused, he replyed blood was drawn on me in thy presence, which thing ought not to be done in the presence of a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of the Peace; <hi>Richard Brown</hi> replyed to this purpose, <hi>viz.</hi> Hold your prating or there shall as much be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain here in the presence of the Court.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>S. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ON the first day of the week, and 29th. of the 4th. month, 1662. At the <hi>Bull and Mouth</hi> there came in a band of Souldiers with Swords and Musquets and other Weapons,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35042:9"/> and they used not a little cruelty with wild, violent actions against the peaceable, innocent and harmless people of the Living and True God, that in quietness and Gods reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and fear were met together; but the Souldiers with much rage did handle them roughly, and tossed their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies unhumanly up and down from place to place without mercy to either Men, Women or Children, and so they drove them forth of the meeting Room, and they carried me [who resisted not evil but gave place to wrath seeing it was so] together with four more to <hi>Pauls Yard,</hi> where for some hours we were kept in hold, and from thence sent to <hi>Newgate,</hi> without appearing first before a Magistrate, and in the said Evening we were set forth with Souldiers and had before <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> to whom I spake these words in the gentle meekness of Christ, saying, Let the fear of God and his peace be set up in thy heart, but he made light of the same and laught, and said he had rather hear a dog bark, with much such like scoffing terms; He charged me with the breach of the Kings Law in meeting together, I said on this wise, The Servants of God in the Apostles dayes were commanded to speak no more in the Name of Jesus, and they answered (and so do I) whether it be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey God or man judge ye; and the matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the three Children and <hi>Daniel,</hi> that with stood the decrees of Kings in such like cases of conscience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, I also spake before him, but oh how he sport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himself in lightness and folly and cruelty, whilest he sate commanding to smite and buffet me on the face, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused me before him which they did not cease to do in his fight; Four or five times they haled me to the ground and abused my body at their feet, and smote me with wicked fists, and rung my neck so as if they would have murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in his presence to do him a pleasure, being men as if he had on purpose educated them for such unreasonable and dishonourable service before his face against the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; Now I seeing that they were not then capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a word from Gods Counsel, surely my heart was broken, and in the same I cryed secretly to the God of my innocency with tears being grieved for the hardness of their hearts.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35042:10"/>
               <p>And after the same manner (instead of justice and mercy) was my friends oppressed &amp; abused in the house in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and before the face of <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> who forthwith having neither justice nor mercy to minister, sent us to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> Prison again, even as lambs worried with wolves and as sheep for the slaughter; Now I had not been but about 14. dayes arrived in <hi>England</hi> my own Nation, and to the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of these proceedings before <hi>R. Brown,</hi> I said on this wise, if Turks and Heathens were here to see these actions, in the presence of a Magistrate thats called a Christian at least they might be ashamed, if they did not defie and abhor, and blaspheme the God of a true Christians life, because of such bruitish and dishonourable actions and proceedings; But some of the moderate beholders being smitten with tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, drew near and said that they were grieved to the heart to see the same. So after this manner, not only we were taken from meeting together in the fear and worship of the true and living God, but also from prison and from judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>as they have done unto me so will they do unto you,</hi> saith Jesus our Lord; and so the Scriptures of truth we witness fulfilled, which turns to us for a testimony, not only against the particular proceedings of <hi>R. B.</hi> but also against the world, because the deeds thereof are evil, and because of which we also suffer, even for the clear, pure testimony of the truth of Jesus.</p>
               <p>And of the 5th. day of the 4th. month were we called to the Sessions, and in the first place the Court ordered and demanded of us to put in sureties to appear at the next Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions or go to prison; when they had read their inditement, nor any witness appearing against us, save <hi>R.B.</hi> on the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat, and when I demanded to see the Inditement first, and thereby to convince us of doing either good or evil before the people, which the Magistrates upon the judgement seat ought to have done, (as I in the fear and authority of God demanded) albeit as to my own particular, together with many friends more we were well satisfied in well doing and guiltlesness in the answer of a good conscience, then it was answered there was no inditement, and therefore the Oath was immediatly tendered to us as a snare, for so much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35042:10"/> as they knew that we could not swear at all either for or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our selves or any man, and therefore committed and hurried away to Prison again, there to abide without bayle till we swear, as saith the Callender, and therefore a child that hath but the least spark of a clear understanding may see what Justice and Judgement is brought forth by <hi>R. B.</hi> whether good or evil, let all the upright in heart Judge.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. Baker.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Case of <hi>Charles Baley,</hi> with three friends more apprehended the 27th. of the 4th. month.</head>
               <p>IT being so that my self and other three Friends came to the old <hi>Baley</hi> (where the Sessions were then held) to hear the Cause of our innocent Brethren who there were brought for the Testimony of a good conscience, and there being arrained at the Bar, it was observed that they had not the liberty given them as common fellons and murtherers had as we with many more were eye witnesses; for instead of shewing the cause of their Imprisonment, as was then desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them pleading that they had not then seen their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers, but instead of answering this their reasonable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest they were sought to be insnared by and with another thing then was first pretended against them, but as they ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to see their accusers face to face, the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was tendred to them, they answered, they came not there to accuse themselves, but desired first to be cleered, or at least shewed the cause of their being brought before the Bench at that time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it being so as aforesaid, that my self with three Friends more were in the back-side of a Merchants Shop not within the Sessions Court, yet notwithstanding we were there apprehended by some Officers and brought before the Bench, who commanded that we should be brought before them, and they inquired of us our Names, but the Friends with me not being contious in themselves of having done wrong unto any, and in the wisdom of God seeing that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35042:11"/> the Spirits of men are set rather to insnare the Innocent then to relieve the oppressed, for which reasons they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to give in their names; but desiring first to know the cause of there being brought there, but none would or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed could justly be shewed them; but I being a Foreigner was free in my self to tell my Name and place of abode, which was in <hi>Mary-Land</hi> in <hi>Virginia,</hi> yet notwithstanding the Oath was tendred unto me, and I urged to take it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the command of Christ, who saith swear not at all, whose righteous command I prefer before the threats and commandments of men, chusing rather to suffer for this cause with the Innocent people of God then to injoy any Liberty whatsoever; And thus we standing in our integrity were committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> from whence a second time we were brought before the Judges who were only our accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, and I being urged to swear the second time, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing that I gave them clearly to know that I was a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rener, and for this cause and no other that I know of am I committed prisoner without bayle until I swear, where I wait with my dear Friends in patience untill God arise and plead our cause.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>C. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>HAving heard in the former part of the Tryal of the same Friends aforesaid, and also of the apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and imprisoning of us, and what violent usage we have endured in our Meetings as is before declared by armed men and rude Souldiers and Military Power which is illegal and directly contrary to the ancient Laws of the Land, and to the Kings late Proclamation of the 17th. of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1660. which expresly prohibits all Officers and Souldiers to ceaze upon, molest or trouble any of the Kings Subjects, unless it be upon a suddain and actual Rebellion and Insurrection, and by the same Proclamation they are charged and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in these words, that no Officers nor Souldiers do presume to apprehend or secure any person or persons, nor to search any houses without a lawful Warrant under the hand and seal of some one or more of the Lords of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Counsel, or Justices of the Peace in their respective Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; And we will that the said Warrants be directed to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35042:11"/> some Constable or other known Legal Officer; and that no Souldiers do otherwise interpose or medle with the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any of the said Warrants then by assisting of the said Constables, and we do hereby declare that all those who shall hereafter be so hardy as to offend against this our Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion shall not only now receive countenance from us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but shall be left to be proceeded against according to our Laws and incur our high displeasure, as persons doing their utmost to bring scandal and contempt upon our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this manner of proceedings of the Major General, his Officers and Souldiers is contrary hereunto, as also unto the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> 9. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 29, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 4 <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. Which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly sayes <hi>[No Free-man shall be taken nor imprison<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, or be disseised of his Free-hold or Liberties, but by the Law of the Land; None shall be imprisoned unless it be by the Law of the Land, and it is established that from henceforth none shall be taken by Petition or Suggestion, unlesse it be by Indictment or Presentment of the good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the same neighbourhood, in due manner, or by process made by Writ Original at the Common Law; Nor that none be put out of his Franchises, unlesse he be duely brought in answer and fore-judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the same by the course of Law, and if any thing be done against the same, it shall be redressed and holden for none. No man of what estate or condition soever he be, shall be taken and imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>isoned, nor disinherited without being brought in answer and due processe of the Law, &amp;c.]</hi> Let the Statutes at large be read, and fully compared with the proceedings of <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> and then let all wise men judge, whether it is we or he that are trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressors of the Laws of the Land. I say,</p>
               <p>By all which it is apparently manifest, that the manner of our taking, and apprehending, and imprisonment, tis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to the Laws of the Land, and to the present Kings own intent, signified in his Proclamation before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; Yet notwithstanding <hi>Richard Brown</hi> seeming to be a man neither regarding Law nor Reason, but casting behind his back the Ancient Laws of <hi>England,</hi> hath thus proceeded as aforesaid, in causing to be apprehended and imprisoned about seven score of us, which is also contrary to the Kings
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35042:12"/> late Proclamation mentioned, and were we not of the spirit to forgive our enemies, and desires not to render evil for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to any man, how might the Major General, his Officers and Souldiers be dealt withall, who hath thus proceeded contrary to the Laws of the Land, but we rather desire his repentance if his day be not over, and he given up for destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then to deal with him after the measure he hath dealt to us, onely we can do no lesse then publish these things to the World, and shall leave all sober men to judge of this case between him and us who are called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now here follows some short account of the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in general of the Court at the general quarter Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions at Old Baley in <hi>London,</hi> concerning the Prisoners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, who partly expected they should have been prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon the late Act of Parliament, being apprehended upon the pretence of the same, though contrary to both the letter and meaning of it, as we should have made manifest if we had been indicted upon the said Act; but as may be supposed, the Court either finding themselves not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prepared, for want of due proceedings according to that Act, or otherwise wanting evidence against the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or else having more envy to inflict upon us, then the late Act would give them ground for, either for these or some other reasons the Court seemed to renounce the said Act, and did not meddle with it, nor prosecute it upon us, seeming thereby to render the work of the Parliament in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid, who had thought good to make his late Act on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose for us.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithstanding Indictments were drawn up against about a hundred of us, in form and manner as hereafter shall be shewed; and the twenty eighth day of the fourth month, being the seventh day of the week, about fifty of us were fetched out of the prison by the Keepers, and led down to the Sessions House, the persons aforesaid mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the former part, being then pleading at the Bar; but no sooner did we appear in the Court, but the Judges on the Bench cryed out away with them, carry them back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in a strange kind of passionate mood; which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly the Keepers did, and lockt us up again in the prison,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35042:12"/> and about an hour after the Keepers came and hurried us out again down to the Court, and being brought into the Court, the Judges looking upon us, cryed again furiously, Away with them, carry them back again, lock them up, away with them, and such like words, which the Goalers did; and thus twice were we hurried to and again, to the astonishment of the beholders, who could not but wonder to see us so led up and down, to and again in so short a space, like as if the Court having enmity enough against us, and could not tell how to inflict it, nor what to do, and this was the onely proceedings in Court towards us that day.</p>
               <p>Again the first day of the fifth month, being the third day of the week, we were called to the Sessions again about 80. of us, and placed at the Fellons Bar, many were called by their names in particular to answer to their Indictments; for they were many of them Indicted in form and manner as hereafter is expressed (to wit.)</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="indictment">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>
                                 <hi>London, ss.</hi>
                              </dateline>
                           </opener>
                           <p>THe Juries for our Lord the King, do present upon their Oath, that — late of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with diverse other persons to the said Juries, unknown to the number of <hi>100.</hi> persons — day of June, in the fourteenth year of the Reign of our Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> the second, of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor of the Faith, &amp;c. with force and arms, &amp;c. in <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. to wit, in the Parish of Saint <hi>Ann</hi> and <hi>Agnes,</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Alders-gate London</hi> aforesaid, under pretence of performing Religious Worship, otherwise then by the Laws of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in this Kingdom is established, unlawfully and tumultuously did gather and assemble themselves together to the great ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his Majesties people, and to the disturbance of the peace of our now Lord the <hi>King,</hi> in contempt of our said Lord the <hi>King</hi> and his Laws, to the evil example of all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35042:13"/> others in the like case offending, and against the Peace of our said Lord and King, his Crown and Dignity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This is the form of the Indictment <hi>verbatim,</hi> being on this wise Indicted, sometimes ten, sometimes six, sometimes two, more or fewer as the Clerk had seen good to joyn us together in several draughs of the Indictments, the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being one and the self same to all, which Indictment being read, they were called severally to answer (sometimes ten, and sometimes six as aforesaid, according as they were drawn up in the indictments) guilty or not guilty, in Form and Matter, as they were indicted; to which the Prisoners made a pause, and would not answer presently neither guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or not guilty, but began to speak something to the Court, as about the manner and nature of their being apprehended and imprisoned by command of Alderman <hi>Brown,</hi> by his Officers and Souldiers, with force of Arms, contrary to the antient Laws of the Land, and contrary to the Kings late Proclamation as aforesaid; And some of the Prisoners did insist much upon this, hoping to have had audience of the Court according to justice, and that the Court would have redressed this grievance, of being thus illegally and violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehended and imprisoned, some being taken out of their own houses by Souldiers, and some out of the Streets, and some out of their peaceable Meetings, &amp; violently hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to prison without either Warrant from Magistrate or Civil Officer, contrary to the Laws in that case made and provided as before is quoted; These things the Prisoners at the Bar were ready to press again and again to the Court, before they would answer to their Indictments, alwayes cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for justice, &amp; the due execution of the Laws of the Land, but of this the Court seemed to take no notice, like as if there had been nothing of injustice in their being thus apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and imprisoned as before is declared, neither were the prisoners suffered to shew at large the manner of their tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and imprisonment, but the Court cryed still, you must plead guilty or not guilty to your Indictment, alwayes pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing it upon the Prisoners, to say guilty or not guilty, and would suffer no other thing to be spoken by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners, though diverse of them had been taken up
<gap reason="missing" extent="8 pages">
                     <desc>〈8 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35042:13"/> out of the street and sent to Newgate by Souldiers, and could no way be supposed to be guilty of the Indictment, but the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners might not declare any thing of this kind, but alwayes it was pressed upon them again and again to say guilty or not guilty, to which at last seeing the Court would not hear them, many of the Prisoners answered not guilty, of the matter not form of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, for it is not unknown to the whole land but that the said Indictment is utterly false, for we can appeal to all sober people, when or where we ever were found to meet with force of Armes, this has never been our practise as the world knowes, and therefore it is a lye and of the Divel who ever chargeth it upon us: and as for our Meetings they have never been tumultuous on our parts, but alwaies quiet and peaceable and in the fear of God and not to the terror of the People nor to the disturbance of the Peace of the King, nor in contempt of the King and his Laws, nor to the evil example of any others, nor against the Peace of the King, his Crown or Dignity: all these things are utterly false we call God, Angels and men to witness, and we leave it to the eternal God to determine the case between us and our Accusers, in the mean time we say woe unto them that makes lies their refuge, God will sweep them away with the Beesome of destruction.</p>
               <p>And when it was asked the Court by some of the Prisoners what Statute or Act of Parliament they were indicted upon, the Recorder answered we were neither indicted upon any Statute, Act of Parliament, or written Law, but were Indicted at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, though what or where that Law is, the Nature and Penalties of it, he did not discover as he ought to have done to the Prisoners, some of whom were ignorant concerning the same. And divers of the said Prisoners having pleaded not guilty, demanded a fair Tryal fortwith according to Justice, and that their Accusers might be brought forth, face to face, for they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired nothing more than a fair Tryal in the face of that Assembly, (being many hundreds of people present looking on) to which the Court answered, they should not be tryed till the next Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions.</p>
               <p>Thus Justice was deferred and delayed, and the Cause of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35042:14"/> Innocent could not be heard, and instead thereof the bonds of the poor prisoners strengthned, and increased, though it was told them by the prisoners, that this was a Goal delivery of Newgate, and they sate there by the Commission of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and they ought to hear and determine and deliver the Goale; and it was much pressed upon them for a present tryal, but it would not be granted by the Court, only it was told the Prisoners that if they would give such and such bayl (which could not in reason be done) they might have their liberty till next Sessions, all them that had pleaded not guilty.</p>
               <p>But divers of the Prisoners perceiving that they were not to have their Tryal this Sessions, but were only to be sent back to Prison again, and also being surprised with his form of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not expecting but that the Indictments would have been drawn upon this latest Act made against us; for these with some other reasons, they refused to plead at all, onely stood much upon the nature of their being imprisoned contrary to Law, which might very well be insisted upon, seeing it was so contrary to the law and divers Statutes as before is shewed, and seeing the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners could not be heard, divers of them did refuse to plead at all, and would not say neither guilty nor not guilty, whereupon the Court seemed to be highly displeased, yet the Prisoners were not without some good reasons of refusing to plead in their form, however the Court proceeded to sentence such as mutes, and told them they would take their Indictments <hi>pro confesso,</hi> and would judge them as guilty of all contained in the Indictment, though the whole Court could not be so ignorant but know that the said Indictments were false, for we never used to meet with force of Armes, nor to the breach of the peace, nor in contempt either of the King or his lawes, as the Indictement signifies; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Court did proceed to Sentence divers of our Friends, as mute, and fined them some an hundred pound, and some an hundred marks, and committed them without bayl or mainprize till payment of the said Fines, where they remain at this present, and not suffered to go abroad to look after their occasions, though necessity require it, divers of them being poor housekeepers in, and about this City.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:35042:14"/>
               <p>And we perceiving how the Court intended co carry the matters against us; some of our freinds were made to cry out against such proceedings, when they saw our Tryal was to be deferred, and whether we pleaded or not pleaded all was one, to Prison we must goe, and that was their purpose whether we were guilty, or not guilty of what was charged upon us; And one freind in particular called to <hi>Richard Brown</hi> in these words, telling him; he was not fit to sit there, for he caused the Son to hang the Father at <hi>Abing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and so told him he was a Murderer and he would prove it, and bid him Repent with such like words. Now this same person had been a Souldier formerly under <hi>Richard Brown</hi> at <hi>Abington;</hi> Hereupon was some disturbance in the Court &amp; they seemed to be displeased at this Charge, whereupon it was commanded that the person should immediately be carried back to Prison, and double Irons put upon him; which was done forthwith, though <hi>Richard Brown</hi> did not seem to deny the thing in the Court, nor clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self from it, though it was very peremtorily charged upon him; at which some of the Prisoners were a little troubled that any such high tearms should be given to any Magistrate upon the Bench (whose place &amp; Office we do respect &amp; honour) and some of them did afterwards speake to the said person that if he had enviously said these words and could not prove them true, he should be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it, and disowned, and should bear his own burthen; for they would not justifie any man that should falsely and maliciously speak these words, and to this very purpose one of the Prisoners wrote a Letter the next day to <hi>Richard Brown</hi> concerning the same, also de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring to know of him whether the thing was really true or false, signifying if these words were falsely and enviously spoken the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son should be denyed by us, and dealt withal according to the Judgement of a slanderer and made an example, &amp;c. Which Letter being delivered into his hands, and he perceiving from who it came, immediately tore it in peices whilest the Messenger was present and no other return of it is until this day.</p>
               <p>Also on the same day in the Court Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> behaving himself somewhat unseemly on the Bench at divers times by whis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perings, and deriding of the Prisoners at the Bar, when it was told
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35042:15"/> him by one of the Prisoners how the Souldiers violently hayled him, and bore him upon their Muskets out of the Meeting towards the Prison, (in a very violent abusive manner, dangerous to have spoyled the man) who was not willing to goe with the Souldiers in that they would not shew him any warrant, for their apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him as in equity he might refuse to goe not knowing, but that they might be Robbers, or Murtherers, seeing they had no War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from any civil Magistrate for what they did in that case; and whilest the freind was making Relation of this at the Bar, <hi>Richard Brown</hi> made answer to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi> If they should have dragged him through all the Kennels in the streets, they had served him right if he would not goe; at which furious speech some of our freinds were moved to speak to the said <hi>Richard Brown</hi> by way of reproof telling him he had many warnings, and visitations in the Love of God but he had slighted them, and he was to be sealed in the wrath of God, and to this effect, &amp;c. Hereupon grew a great disturbance in the Court in so much that one of the Goalors came with his cane lifted up, and struck and beat divers of the Prisoners that were standing at the Bar, not regarding whom he hit, insomuch divers were much bruised by his blows; and this was in the very face of the Court, and some say <hi>Richard Brown</hi> was heard to say pull him down, others say he said knock him down, but we cannot certainly say whether it was, however the disturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was so great in the Court, and the blows so violent, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Spectators cryed out, and some said Murder, murder, and asked if they would suffer men to be murthered in the Court, whereupon one of the Sheriffs in person came down from his seat to still the people, and to stop the man from beating the Prisoners, and many cryed out it was a shameful peice of work to suffer poor men to be beaten in that cruel manner in the face of the Court, and the like they had never seen; but instead of reproof, <hi>Richard Brown</hi> said to the Prisoners to this purpose, that if their were any of them kild their blood should be on their own head, as if it were on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to encourage the man to beat our freinds; Also the common Hang-man stood among the Prisoners threatning them, with a Gag in his hand ready to Gag any of them that should speak any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35042:15"/> thing, and so they were resolved against the Prisoners to carry on their purpose against them, and twas their main designe to stop the Prisoners from speaking or declaring any thing of their case to the Court, and this was discerned by the spectators, and it was too much manifest by the Goalers Cane, and the Hangmans Gag, both there ready to stop the mouths of the Innocent, and to affright them by their Instruments of cruelty, which were prepared against the poor Prisoners, that desired nothing but Justice and the due execution of the Law, and that they might be heard to manifest their case and unjust proceedings towards them hitherto, but it could not be obtained.</p>
               <p>And having called divers Companies, for they were indicted in several Companies, sometime six, sometimes more or fewer together accord as the Clark judged meet, as before I have shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, this was their proceedings towards them all, they put the Prisoners strictly to answer guilty or not guilty, and would hear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, and those that said not guilty, they took their plea and promised them a Tryal next Sessions, and those that would not plead they condemned as mutes, and took their Indictments <hi>pro Confesso</hi> as is before shewed, and sent them all back again to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son as they had called them in particular companies, and before half of them were called over the Mayor left the Bench, he and his Officers and the Sword before him and passed quite away, the Recorder and two Aldermen being lest on the Bench, yet they called over more of the Prisoners and read their Indictments, and proceeded as before against them, notwithstanding the Mayor and Sword (being the Authority of the City) were gone, and these continued about an hour after, and then adjourned the Court till the seventh day following, which was to be the fifth day of this instant, the Court departed and all the Prisoners were carryed back to the prison again, and this is the sum of the proceedings in Court the first day of this month.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:35042:16"/>
               <head>Here followes an Account of what passed the fifth day of this Month.</head>
               <p>THe Court being come together in <hi>Old Bayley,</hi> the Prisoners were again had down to the Court, all them who had not been called the day before, and the Court being called and the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion read, prisoners were set to the Bar and called in divers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar companies, as the day before, and their Indictments read, the same in forme and manner, and also for matter as before is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, to which, the prisoners were required to answer guilty or not guilty, and according as they had done the day before, so these would not immediately answer, guilty or not guilty, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to be heard as concerning the illegal apprehending and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoning of them, having very much to say both from Law and Reason, in that case pressing very hard upon the Court for hearing, but was wholly denyed to be heard any thing but guilty or not guilty, to which at last some answered not guilty, and those the Goaler took into custody again, the Court promising them they should be tryed the next Sessions, and divers of the prisoners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused to answer in their terms, for which they were fined as the day before for Mutes, the Indictment taken <hi>pro confesso,</hi> though divers did in effect plead not guilty: in these words one said I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny I am guilty, and I am not canscious, and I can say I am not guilty and <hi>non reissum,</hi> and such words as these signifying fully in effect not guilty, yet because the very words in the same terms were not expressed, therefore they sentenced them as mutes. So strickt and narrow was the spirit of the Court, that not for want of substance at all or true intent or meaning, but for want of form of speech only were men condemned, and such a fine imposed upon them, and to lye in prison till payment, and particularly one man being called to answer to his Indictement, guilty or not guilty, he stood silent a little time, and did not presently answer, having something from the Lord upon his spirit to speak to them, then Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> scoffed and said we shall have a Revellation by and by, in a little time the person spoke some words to them in the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35042:16"/> fear of God saying, <hi>How long will you oppress the innocent! How long will you persecute the Righteous seed of God, &amp;c.</hi> In which time of his speaking Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> cryed Aha, Aha, and said will you have any <hi>Wallfleet Oysters,</hi> and have you any <hi>Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chin-stuffe</hi> maids, thus scornfully imitating Oyster women upon the Bench, and presently the person was taken away from the Bar, and also when a prisoner at the bar said he could not for conscience sake forbear meeting among the people of God, it was replyed to him by Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> in these words, Conscience <hi>a doggs tail,</hi> Also when Alderman <hi>Adams</hi> spoke to one of the prisoners saying, <hi>I am sorry to see you here,</hi> sorry said Alderman <hi>Brown, what should you be sorry for,</hi> yes said Alderman <hi>Adams</hi> yes he is a sober man, then <hi>Brown</hi> replied there was never a sober man amongst them, yes said Alderman <hi>Adams</hi> he will not be drunk, then <hi>Brown</hi> replyed, (drunk) it is not matter if they could not eat neither, and thus did Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> express himself in such terms divers times on the Bench, shewing such passion and fury against the Prisoners at the bar, that the spectators took much notice of him, discommending his carriage exceedingly, who should have been an equal Judge, sitting in the place of judgement, and yet accused the Prisoners, and gave them threatning and deriding language not like the place of a Judge, insomuch that it is beleived that the hearts of all the people were set against him to observe such words and carriages from him who seemed not to have words bad enough to express of the poor prisoners, for at a certain time before, two Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs being upon their tryal for robbing a house, he told them (being then Mayor of the City) they were the verriest Rogues in <hi>England</hi> except it were the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and thus he vented forth himself continually against the innocent.</p>
               <p>Thus was the Proceedings that day in the Court, the priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners being called in several companies as they was packt up in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments drawn up against them, till such time they were called all over whom they had indicted, for they had not indicted all the prisoners though generally, except some few all were taken from Meetings as before is shewed. And these they called to the bar who were willing to declare their case, and the nature and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35042:17"/> manner of their taking and imprisoning as others attempted to do, for it was the main weighty matter, that the Prisoners would have first insisted upon and that according to both Law and Conscience, for they had both these on their side to condemne the manner of their apprehending, and imprisoning, and the Prisoners cryed let us see the face of our accusors what have you against us, and what have we done &amp; we desire Justice &amp;c. But instead of this the Oath of Allegiance was tendred to them, Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> often crying to them (having no Indictment drawn nor any thing against them,) will you take the Oath, hold him the Book, what say you say your hands upon it, will you take it, &amp;c. And thus he said to divers, and the Prisoners desired to reason the case with the Court, and to shew them that it was not a faire not equal way of proceeding, that they should be imprisoned pretendedly upon the aforesaid late Act of Parliament for meeting together, and imprisoned some of them six weeks, and some a month for that cause, and now expected their Tryal, and to see the face of their Accusers, and for them now to have the Oath tendred to them, seemed to be but a Trap and Snare to encrease their bonds, when as they could prove nothing against them on the Act for which they were pretendedly imprisoned and now to tender the Oath to them, whom they knew before, for Conscience sake would refuse to swear, this seemed to be no good Justice nor faire dealing, and further it was desired to be shewed unto them that the Statutes requiring the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance was never intended for us, as the very titles and preambles of the Statutes do shew 30 <hi>Iacobi</hi> Chap. 4th. and the 7th. Chap. 6. and it would have been shewed them that it was altogether improper, and not according to the true intent and meaning of the said Statutes to tender the Oath to us, at that time and on that occasion especially, and that it appeared they made use of the Oath now meerly as a Snare, and this was told them though they refused to hear much, what could be said in this case by the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but kept them close to the question, will you take it, or will you not; Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> always crying hold them the Book; hold them the Book, but the Prisoners for Conscience sake could not swear at all especially upon that occasion seeing the Oath was
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35042:17"/> only put to them as a snare, whereupon the Court proceeded ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their refusal; though some did not absolutely deny to swear, but desired first to reason the case with them, and sentenced them to be had back again to prison, there to lye without bayl or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ize, till they take the said oath: And such manner of proceeding we leave the world to judge of, though we are like to suffer by it, that instead of being brought to a legal tryal for the fault supposed against us, and for which we had suffered divers weeks imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and no accusor appearing against us, nor yet legally deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by due course of Law as we ought to have been, but on the contrary still to deteyn us in Prison to the ruening of our persons and Families, if the mercy of God prevent not; Now to proffer the Oath to us so unseasonably and not according to their own Laws by which that Oath is required, let the Lord determine this case.</p>
               <p>And also there were several of the said Prisoners brought to the Bar, that had never been before any Magistrate since their being apprehended by the rude Souldiers (as before is declared,) and crayed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and never brought before any civil Magistrate nor examined, neither had any legal Commitment not according to the Law of the Land, and some of these were called by name in the Court, and neither Indictment against them, nor any to accuse them, and these were required by the Court to put in Baile for their appearance the next Sessions, which the Prisoners were not willing to do because in all reason and Law, they should have been discharged because no man appeared against them; and it was counted an unreasonable thing among the Heathens, for <hi>Festus</hi> did account it an unreasonable thing to send a Prisoner and not to signifie the crime against him, <hi>Acts</hi> 25.27. <hi>ver.</hi> And according to the Laws of <hi>England</hi> it ought not to be done, but these were sent to Prison and nothing charged against them, nor never brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore legal Authority to examine them before they were imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and when they were brought to the Court, no man appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to accuse them, and yet still deteyned close prisoners, and not released according to the due course of Law, if this be Justice we are yet ignorant and know nothing, and it is not long since a Judge
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35042:18"/> upon the Bench <hi>(viz.) Windham</hi> in the Lent Assizes 1660. holden at <hi>Thelford</hi> for the County of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> did openly reprove some of the Justices upon the Bench, because they committed men to Prison and had bound over none to pesecute them, nor had any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence against them in the Court, when the Prisoners were at the Bar; which practice of the Justices was sharply reproved by the said Judge on the Bench, as well it might be; and this was partly the case of these Prisoners committed to Prison, and brought to the Bar, and no accuser against them, neither Prosecutor nor evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and we know it is usual to make Proclamation in the Court, when Prisoners stands upon their deliverance, if any can come forth and accuse them, otherwise to be discharged, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of doing us this Justice, when no Prosecutor nor evidence was against us, then put him the Oath and see if he will swear, and let him give Baile and put in security, or else send him to Prison again; <hi>From this kind of Iustice good Lord deliver us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And again there was divers had been Prisoners, for some weeks, whose names they had not, for they had refused till that time to tell their names, and then being asked by the Court the reason why they did not tell their names, it was replied by the Prisoners because they had never yet been brought before a Civil Magistrate nor before any that had legal Authority to demand their names, and they did not refuse as though they were afraid to tell their names, for they had done nothing for which they had a reason to deny their names, but being seized upon in that manner in their Meetings by a company of rude Souldiers, more like murtherers then men intrusted with any Authority to seize upon men, and they had done and should refuse to tell their names to such kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, though they were ready there to tell there names to the Magistrate, which accordingly some of them did, yet notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were all sent back to Prison again, like as if that Sentence had been determined by the Court, whatsoever their case should appear to be, so without either exception of persons or cases all of our freinds that appeared before them were recommitted to close Prison, there to remain we know not how long, even till God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise and plead our Cause, for as appeares the Rulers are resolved
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35042:18"/> whether by Law, without Law, or contrary to Law, to keep us in Prison without releif, though we have Justice and Truth of our side, and are peaceable men in life and conversation according to Truth, and no man can detect us, and are peceable and quiet in our Meetings, and desires nothing but that we may live a quiet life in all Godliness and honesty under the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here followeth an account how several of the aforesaid Prisoners were used by Alderman <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> when first brought before him.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Isaac Merrit,</hi> coming before him, he caused his hat to be pulled off with great violence, and because it being put in his hand, he covered his head therewith, the said <hi>Rich. Brown</hi> ordered it to be pulled off, so that his head might be pulled down, which was done with such violence, and as if they would have broke his neck.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Brain</hi> being taken in the street and not in any meeting, was laid hold on and garded before <hi>Richard Brown</hi> with a band of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and one of the Officers with his Halbord had at the end thereof a nail drove in, and run it at the peoples sides which stood in the yard near the mouth in <hi>Martins Lane:</hi> and when the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named party was before the said <hi>R. Brown,</hi> he gave order that he should be pulled down to the ground six or seven times, &amp; when he was down they beat his head against the ground and stampt upon him, and when that he was risen again, this <hi>Richard Brown</hi> bad them to pull off his nose also, which they spared not to assay to do, pulling him violently by the nose, and when he arose again they pulled him to the ground by the hair of the head, and by the hair they pulled him up again, and when he would have spoken in his own behalf, seeing such cruelty was used upon him, <hi>Richard Brown</hi> bad them to stop his mouth, whereupon they struck him on the mouth and stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his nose and mouth also, by which means he could not fetch his breath for a time, and so they played with their fingers upon his mouth which was an object of derision for <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> who laughed at the cruel and inhumane actions, and at the end sent him to Jayle not having any just ground for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tho. Spire</hi> being brought before <hi>R. Brown,</hi> he commanded his hat to be pulled off, and because it was not done with such violence
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35042:19"/> as he intended, he caused it to be put upon his head again, saying it should not be pulled off so easily, and when he bid that it should be pulled off again, it was done with such force as the said <hi>Tho. Spire</hi> was pulled up from the ground by the hair of his head, and because when <hi>Richard Brown</hi> asked his name he did not tell it presently he commanded the Souldiers to force open his mouth, which they did with such violence as they made it bleed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Hill</hi> being brought before him as abovesaid, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his hat to be pulled off so that his head might be bowed down, which was done so that they bowed him down to the ground, and being pulled to the ground, <hi>Richard Brown</hi> commanded he should be pulled up by the hair of the head which was done, and because he did not tell him his name presently when he asked, he caused the Souldiers in derision to open his mouth by force.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Cook</hi> being brought before him, he commanded his hat to be pulled off so that his head might be bowed down, so a souldier pulled it off and bowed him neer the ground and pulled off part of the hair of his head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arthur Baker</hi> being brought before him he caused his hat to be pulled off with such violence as his body was bowed down to the very ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Geo. Ableson</hi> being brought before <hi>Alderman Brown,</hi> he caused his hat instead of pulling off, to be pulled hard on to his head, and so plucked it downward till his body was forced to the ground, and when they had plucked him up by the hair of the head, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to pluck him down again, which he did for five times one after another, and they plucked him up again by the hair, till the sides of his head were sore, and his neck also much pained for some daies after, and he received a blow on the face which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him to stagger neer the ground, and with their violent pulling down his hat over his face, caused his nose to bleed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nic. Blithhold</hi> being brought before him, coming with his usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Garments, he took off his hat with both hands, endeavouring to pull him down to the ground, and in regard he fell not quite to the ground forwards, then he pusht him to throw him backwards, and then he thrust him out of his house, and gave him a kick on the leg, and thrust him out of his yard.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35042:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Lacy</hi> being brought before him, he asked his name, and because he did not tell it him presently, violently shuf'd him out of his house, and the Alderman himself gave him a blow on the face, and with his hands violently shuf'd him out of the yard.</p>
               <p>After this manner were the proceedings of <hi>Alderman Brown</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards these persons, and divers others of the prisoners that were brought before him, so shamful for a Magistrate, that tis scarce fit to be mentioned being a reproach to the Government, that a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of the Law should beat and abuse people contrary to the Law, and such is the violence of that spirit by which he is acted against the people of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> that he hath often given very threatning words behind their backs, to divers persons that have modestly and discreetly enquired of him about that people: as that their estates should first wholly be taken away, and then he would send them into Countries without Inhabitant to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured of wild beasts, and to be torn in peices by savage creatures, and if they had any children they should be left upon the Parishes where they dwelt, and the Parishes should be forced to maintain them; further often saying, he would not give over to imprison them, and afflict them as long as there was one of them left alive, with such like threatning words expressed, which can be witnessed by divers that heard him, and these actions and words, his doings and threats before mentioned truly considered by wise and sober men, It is left to their judgements whether this man be a reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judge over this poor people, who thus endeavours and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens their destruction, and whether he appears not to be their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute enemy rather then their equal Judge: well if these procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings prosper long it must be when there is no God, as one of the said Prisoners expressed at the Bar: and if these waies and actions bring honour, and happiness to the Government and to the King, then we may say <hi>God regards not the cry of the afflicted,</hi> but he hath ceased to be just in his judgments, nay it was well observed by one very lately who came only in love to visite the said prisoners in <hi>Newgate;</hi> one that loves and honours the King as much as any man, (to his power and command that he hath under him) none excepted, in these words he was perswaded, that the said <hi>Brown</hi> was one of the greatest Enemies that the King had alive this day, and that by such his cruel proceedings, he turned the hearts of his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35042:20"/> from him; and caused the affections of his his people to be abated; and such proceedings cannot but undoe us all in the end &amp;c. And indeed if wise men do but consider it as the matter truely is, they will easily give their Judgements accordingly, though yet we are sufferers and may suffer yet more, if it were even to death or banishment yet these things do make in their tendancy and effect, to the ruine of the King and his Government, if it prove not so, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the matters and causes be forthwith regulated,) some Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is deputed from me, but in ages to come it will be witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>VVE the people of God being met together in a peaceable meeting at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> upon the 13th. day of the fifth Month, there came in a Leivetenant with several files of Souldiers, with Swords, Guns, and match lited, and laid violent hands on us, and told us that they had an Order to carry us away, &amp; the Officer commanded the Souldiers to look to us the prisoners, whilest he went and searcht the Room for others, and came out and said that there was no more men, but commanded the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to secure us the Prisoners, and so had us away to <hi>Pauls</hi>-yard and put us up into a Room, and set a guard of souldiers on us until they came and fetch us away.</p>
               <p>Then about an hour or two after the Officers with their weapons and Canes, and Souldiers came rudely again into the Meeting with their Muskets and lite matches, Crying which is he, which is he, and layd violent hands on two of us, and hayled us out by force the Officers giving charge to the Souldiers to look to their Prisoners, who kept us in the street while they haled the rest out. Also one called Leivtenant <hi>Newland</hi> taking one of us in the yard, who was not in the Meeting, carryed us all to <hi>Pauls</hi> where they kept us for a time, with the freinds they had taken before, and then brought us all to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where we remained several hours, being then taken out again fifteen in number, by a Captain and souldiers, and they brought us before <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> and he commanded us to stand bare, we being innocent standing still, one pulled off our Hats, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d pull them off head and all to ground, then he called for one of us to come nearer, and he asked my name, I told him, and the place of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d, which when he heard he said, they are sent for all the Nation over, I said nay, we are not sent for, but we are sent,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35042:20"/> he also said that a <hi>Quaker</hi> should not have a being in <hi>England;</hi> to which I answered, The <hi>Quakers</hi> shall have a being in <hi>England</hi> when all these bodys of ours are layd in the dust: then they being in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion about taking us, having nothing to lay to our charge worthy of bonds, Alderman <hi>Brown</hi> said having our hats on was enough, for it was condemnation to keep the hat on; I asked him to shew me by what Law, then he was full of wrath &amp; commanded to take me to Prison, and to put me by my self among the Fellons, I being vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently haled out, I spake as I went out, and one called a Captain dashed me on my face with his staffe that made me to spit blood, so away to <hi>Newgate</hi> I was sent and put in the darke hole; the said Alderman commanded them when I was out, to put a Gag or a Handcarchif in my mouth, and after he sent twelve more of them to me, who were also put in the hole where the condemned men are put after Sentence; and two freinds he sent to Bridewel, and we yet remaine in common Goale in <hi>Newgate</hi> amongst Fellons, and we are Prisoners for the truth of the most high God.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iohn Shield, Rob. Pote, Anthony Skelington, &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THus ye have heard of the proceedings thus far, and the present state of our case is, we are now about Seven score of us Prisoners in this place, remaining upon the accounts before mentioned, and divers of our freinds when they were first brought into <hi>Newgate,</hi> were put into a very dark nasty stinking place called the hole, where they always put the condemned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons between their Sentence and Execution, and some of our freinds have been kept there 24 hours, and then put up into the Chapel, so many together that they could not all ly upon the floore, but were crouded and thronged in a pittifull manner, some laying in Hamacks, and some no lodging at all, but divers have been nessitated to lay upon the Leads all night without doors, and so thronged have we been within, that we have been near stiffled with extraordinary heart, in so much that it hath been dangerous to cause sicknesses and diseases, but the mercy of the Lord hath preserved us general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in health, except some few who have been visited with sickness for a time, and only two are departed this life, one of which was a fresh lively young man, and being put into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k noysome hole before mentioned, where condemned persons are put, he took his sickness there, and on his death-bed often he would cry out of the noysome stinking Prison, as the occasion of his distemper, and also it was the Judgement of both the Jurys, that passed on on each of the dead bodys; (for any of the prisoners dying, a Jury must pass upon them to finde out the cause of their death,) That though they dyed of Natural sickness, to wit Feavers, yet the occasion of their sickness might possible be their straight imprisonment in such noysome Prisons and so many together, yea are not all these things regarded but we are still thronged up,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35042:21"/> and deteyned in cruel bonds being a great many poor men amongst us, whose poor famalies are exposed to ruine thereby, their poor wives and Children crying out daly for want of husbands and fathers, their Trads ruined, and their Customers complaining, and thus the ruine of many is threatned by reason of this hard imprisonment, yet little notice at all can be taken of this by any in Authority, but all hearts shut up and pitty and compassion fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and the innocent suffering under the oppressions of men and no man regards it, and the deep sense of this our suffering being upon our Brethren that are at Liberty, and desiring in their souls to be instrumental some way for our releif, being one with us in the cause for which we do suffer, were moved of the Lord about thirty of them to present these following lines in manuscript as directed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the Mayor and Sheriffs of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOrasmuch as it hath so come to pass, that many of our friends to the number of <hi>7</hi> score are now close prisoners in <hi>Newgate,</hi> being violently taken and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d by rude Souldiers, and armed men out of our peaceable meetings, which we hold only for the worship of God, &amp; whereas divers of the said prisoners are very poor men, some of them being poor housekeepers, &amp; others among them poor servants in &amp; about this City, and by reason of their close imprisonment, not being permitted by their keepers to goe about any of their occasions though necessity often required it; and forasmuch as the Families of the said poor Prisoners are exposed to utter ruine, by reason of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> said imprisonment, and also being kept so many together in close noysome rooms in this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer season, it hath occasioned diseases and sickness, in so much that two of them are departed this life, and others are sick at this present; and more liable to the same danger, if not timely prevented; Therefore we their freinds and brethren who are one with them in their sufferings, and afflicted with them, and do own the same cause for which they suffer; do desire that you would take into your considerations their sad estate, and finde some way how they may be releived, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Families may not be utterly ruined, nor their persons exposed to death, and if no other way can be found for their releif, if they may not have their Liberty to follow heir occasions for some weeks, or until such time as you shall call for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m; which we desire on their behalfs, and are here ready to give our words that they shall become Prisoners again as you shall appoint them; and if no other way can be found, then we a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of us do present our bodies to you, offering them freely to relieve our afflicted, and oppressed brethern, and are ready to go into their places, and suffer as Prisoners in their rooms for your security, that so many of the poorest of them (as we are here) may have their liberty to go about their needfull occasions, whether it be for some weeks, or till you shall call for them, as you see meet in your wisdoms, all which we do in humility of heart and sincerity of our minds in the fear of God and Love to our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that they may not perish in Prison, and in love to you that Innocent blood and oppression may not come upon you but be prevented from ever being charged against you</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>This was pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ented to the Mayors and Sheriffs of <hi>London</hi> by about <hi>30</hi> of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ren
<date>the <hi>17th.</hi> of the <hi>5th.</hi> Month, <hi>1662.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>